<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Kabelsalat</title>
    <link>https://philmassie.github.io/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Kabelsalat</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://philmassie.github.io/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>PU Learning</title>
      <link>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20190111/pu_learning/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20190111/pu_learning/</guid>
      <description>Introduction A challenge that keeps presenting itself at work is one of not having a labelled negative class in the context of needing to train a binary classifier. Typically, the issue is paired with horribly imbalanced data sets and pressed for time, I have often taken the simplistic route of sub-sampling the unknown set and treating them as unknowns. Obviously this isn&amp;rsquo;t ideal as the unknown set is contaminated and as a result the classifiers dont train that well.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>R Netcdf cheatsheet</title>
      <link>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20160804/r_netcdf_cheatsheet/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 04 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20160804/r_netcdf_cheatsheet/</guid>
      <description>Introduction I recently promised a &amp;ldquo;NetCDF in R&amp;rdquo; cheat sheet to a friend, and I thought it might make a useful tutorial. NetCDF files are often used to distribute gridded, multidimensional spatial data such as sea surface temperature, chlorophyll-a levels and so on. NetCDF is more than just a file format, and so googling it can be a little intimidating. I hope this helps make these files a little easier to use in R.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>South African municipal elections 2016</title>
      <link>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20160714/election_effort/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 14 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20160714/election_effort/</guid>
      <description>Introduction With South Africa&amp;rsquo;s municipal elections in a few days time (3rd August 2016), I wondered about the effort being expended by the parties in each district or municipality. Has it increased or decreased since the 2011 elections? I must point out that I am not a political analyst or a political scientist. I am nevertheless a scientist with an appreciation for analytics.
Employing and promoting candidates costs money. Assuming that our political parties don&amp;rsquo;t have infinite financial resources it follows that investigating where they invest their resources may be a reasonable proxy for effort.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Windrose Plots</title>
      <link>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20160630/ggplot2_wind_rose/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 30 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20160630/ggplot2_wind_rose/</guid>
      <description>Style for changing title colour depending on photo  div.post-heading h1, div.post-heading h2, div.post-heading span.meta { color: midnightblue; }  Introduction This is another post regarding some plots that I needed to make for a publication. As before, I relied heavily on Stack Exchange and many other sites for figuring out how to get my plot looking the way I needed it to, and so this is my attempt to contribute back to the broader community.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Greyscale Contour Plots</title>
      <link>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20160622/ggplot2_contours/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://philmassie.github.io/post/20160622/ggplot2_contours/</guid>
      <description>Introduction Preparing figures for publication can take a long time (well it does for me anyway), and I relied very heavily on numerous online resources to figure out some of the dos and don&amp;rsquo;ts. Obviously I owe massive thanks to the hundreds of blogs and Stack Exchange questions and answers I relied on. Where I can, I will try to link to them.
Additionally, this tutorial covers a little bit about working with reshaped gridded data, shape files, GeoTIFF data and even a simple homemade polygon.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>